A:pada:m apaharta:ram
da:ta:ram sarva-sampada:m
Lo:ka:bhira:mam Sri:Ra:mam
bhu:yo bhu:yo nama:myaham
Jai Sri:manna:ra:yana.
Dear devotees,
when we set out to begin
some task,
why are we doing it?
What is its aim?
Who is involved, what must be done —
only after knowing these
do we begin it. Likewise, when we
take up a scripture,
to read it — why should we read it,
what should we learn,
what benefit will it bring us? —
knowing this,
if we feel it will be of use to us,
then we make the chance to read it,
or to do more.
The Bhagavad Gi:tha too —
for whom, and to reveal what —
knowing this, we should begin it.
Usually
everyone keeps saying, "Oh, the Gi:tha
is a very great scripture,"
they keep thinking so. But what is
its purpose, and for whom?
In the Gi:tha there is
business management,
there is personality development,
there is science, there is philosophy,
there is theology in it,
and many morals too,
this is there, that is there,
so many things — that is how we
talk about the Gi:tha. But when we
touch that scripture,
what we must gain from it,
what we must learn — if we have
clarity about that, we then try
to grasp it from within it.
Now suppose we call the Prime Minister,
"Sir, sweep the roads a little."
If we asked that — well, he could
sweep the roads too;
he may even sweep them. But if sweeping
roads were the purpose,
you would not need that man
to do that work;
someone else would do. There are tasks
only this person can do.
So when receiving such things —
what only he can give —
is the main purpose, then we approach him;
that is how we should.
Not because we got hold of him,
to chatter about this and that,
or to set him to other work —
that only shows our own ignorance,
our own incapacity. Now, when we take
up a scripture like the Gi:tha,
when we bring it up,
what is its purpose?
Merely to teach science? For that,
there are plenty of science books;
go to them and learn all that.
You need not take the Gi:tha
and have to get that
from the Gi:tha alone.
No. Say it is to learn morals —
there are plenty of books for that;
go into them and learn
those ethics and rules there.
No — is the Gi:tha meant to teach us
some management skills?
There are plenty of management courses;
go there and
they will explain all the details;
you can learn those there.
Or to teach rules about food and such?
For that there are enough
eminent physicians; through them
you can learn and obtain those.
So, does the Gi:tha speak
of such things
or not? That is not the question. But if
we know the main aim of the Gi:tha,
then wherever we go, whatever we see —
does it lead us toward that aim
or not? Or through it,
are we able
to attain that aim or not? —
recognizing this becomes our duty.
What is the main aim of the Gi:tha?
Teaching Arjuna his duty
is one thing —
set that aside. If He had begun
mainly only
for that, then once He finished
instructing Arjuna that day, its task
would be over. After that
it would not be needed again;
for this age it would be
of no use to us either.
No — it would have remained
confined to that one occasion.
But the Gi:tha is not a scripture
spoken only for Arjuna,
only to spur him to battle.
Then for what was it spoken?
For humankind —
from when they are born on this earth
until they pass away,
knowing what to do makes
the tasks they must do worthy ones —
this it must teach. And how
should those tasks be done?
The devotion to duty
that all humankind needs —
how it should be — because man
had to be taught this,
teaching that is the main purpose
of His coming as Krushna.
Thinking so, He took Arjuna
as a pretext, an excuse,
arranged it that way,
and delivered this through him —
this is what we must grasp.
The other things are in it too;
Yukta:ha:ra-viha:rasya — learn to eat
rightly; yukta-svapna:vabo:dhasya —
the "early to bed, early to rise"
sayings — those too
are there. Other rules are not absent.
But teaching those rules
is also meant to lead somewhere —
namely, that
man must know his duty
and act upon it.
For all humanity — to teach this,
the Gi:tha came.
That is why the Gi:tha was
divided into three parts.
First six chapters, second six,
third six — eighteen
chapters in all.
The first six chapters
came to establish the A:thma,
its true nature. These, elsewhere,
we will not find. Go into management
courses, you won't learn them;
into morals, you won't know it;
into science, even less.
Going anywhere else, it is hard
to know it. To learn that, you
must come only to the Gi:tha.
Coming to the Gi:tha and
saying "I'll seek those in it"
is folly. And saying it omits them,
raising objections against it —
that too is uncalled for.
The first six chapters were named the
A:thma Shatkam. The nature of the A:thma
is what it explains to us.
Now the second six chapters
were named the Bhakthi Shatkam.
Bhakthi means love. Toward which
reality should this love be turned?
Toward God. Who is God,
how is He, where
is He, what does He do, what is your
bond with Him, what must He do for you, what
you long for, the One you take refuge in —
how far is it possible? All this must be known.
To reveal all this, a six-chapter part
sits in the middle of the Gi:tha. Its
name — the second Shatkam was
called the Bhakthi Shatkam.
After these were spoken,
the doubts that arose in Arjuna —
"if He explains a little, I can
listen and resolve them" —
once that courage came, all said in the
first and second six — twelve chapters —
was once put in order
and consolidated,
and wherever there were
some stop-gaps in it,
some dots needing filling,
if any, all those too were added,
to tell it completely. As these last
six chapters came after, it was named the
Pu:rva-she:sham — meaning
"the remainder of what was said before" —
that is what it was named.
Thus in three parts it was
delivered. An eighteen-chapter scripture,
with Arjuna
taken as the occasion,
instructed by Sri: Krushna —
a most exalted scripture, a spiritual
scripture, the Bhagavad Gi:tha.
In it, the first four chapters —
He revealed a certain grief,
a sorrow
that Arjuna had. For that sorrow
to lift, his power of discernment
had been destroyed. Discernment
means to analyze and
look — that capacity
had diminished.
What must one analyze? One must discern
between the body and the A:thma.
This discerning, they say, is the very
first among the means for one to improve.
Seven means were taught: vive:ka, vimo:ka,
abhya:sa, kriya, anavasa:da, kalya:na, anuddharsha —
thus seven means. Of those seven,
the very first is vive:ka, and with it
He began. Vive:ka does not
mean cleverness —
vive:ka means the ability
to distinguish things apart,
that is its meaning — discernment.
In what should this discernment be made?
Namely: the body and the A:thma are
two — begin here. How did we know this?
How do I get clarity on it? If the food
you eat is good, all is good — your thinking
is what must form in you. For your
thinking to be good, first the fuel
put into it must be good. The fuel is
the food we eat — good food must be taken.
So what is good food? By what do we
decide the goodness of food?
Namely sa:tvika, ra:jasa, ta:masa —
recognizing these, whatever is unfit
we keep away; whatever is needed
we grasp and take. By such food's
influence, the thinking that arises
in you — if you can analyze this body
and this A:thma both and see them,
then that is named vive:ka.
It begins with what is called
a:ha:ra-suddhi — purity of food.
In our scriptures too, the very first
thing said is just this — "a:ha:ra-
suddhau sattva-suddhih;
sattva-suddhau
dhruva: smruthih; smruthi-lambhe
sarva-granthi:na:m vipramo:kshah."
First, a:ha:ra-suddhau — if the
food is good — sattva-suddhih:
the mind becomes good. Sattva means
the mind. Good food, good mind.
Why should the mind be good?
Sattva-suddhau —
dhruva: smruthih: it is through the
mind that jna:na flows into you, so this
flow of jna:na must run smoothly,
unobstructed — no kind of refuse
should get into it; that stream,
that current, must be clean.
It must be pure; then from within it
the water that is jna:na
flows freely.
If that flow runs unbroken,
without stopping again and again,
if it flows steadily,
then it is named dhruva: smruthih —
a steady, settled remembrance,
we say. If this proceeds rightly,
then within,
all the doubts that exist go away;
all the knots loosen.
The direct vision of one's true nature
that should arise, arises.
Whatever you must attain, you attain.
Whatever a human birth is meant to attain,
that you attain.
Sarva-granthi:na:m vipramo:kshah —
all the knots of karma that bind you
fall away too, and you
gain great freedom.
This the Upanishad told us.
So — purity of food: the first thing to
eat is food; without it there is no life.
So the food we take must be good —
and again, how to decide that?
For that, again, some marks
were stated in it.
Ja:thithah — and if someone somehow
contaminates it, those are a:sraya defects;
or if something falls in temporarily
and it is defiled, they call it nimitta.
Ja:thi, a:sraya, nimitta:t,
adushta:t anna:t — ka:ya-suddhih.
This was named vive:ka. That is, things
must not be ja:thi-defiled. Some things
by their very nature carry
certain kinds of qualities.
Some are pungent, some sour,
some sweet — this is naturally their
trait. Likewise, some are by nature
sa:tvika, some
by nature ra:jasa, some by nature
ta:masa. Those that are so by nature —
whichever is sa:tvika for you,
those you should carefully
select, pick up.
The ja:thi-defiled ones,
do not let them come near.
So — ja:thi, a:sraya:
whoever handles it, whoever it reaches
you through — such persons'
influence too inevitably falls
upon that substance at times, so
such a one — one without right
thinking, without proper
devotion, without proper fitness —
by the handling of such people,
by their contact, see that this substance
is not spoiled. A:sraya-adushta:t; ja:thi-
adushta:t; a:sraya-adushta:t;
nimitta-adushta:t.
Nimitta means something fell into it
temporarily — some insect fell in,
an ant fell in, a hair fell in,
a nail fell in,
something falling in temporarily,
or mixing in, or being met with — the
defects that arise from that. This we
call a nimitta defect. By such a nimitta
too, that which is not spoiled —
ja:thi-adushta:t, a:sraya-adushta:t,
nimitta-adushta:t anna:t —
taking such food as fuel,
then, if it is supplied
to the running of this body,
ka:ya-suddhih —
your body becomes well,
good — it becomes one that obeys,
that does as you say.
If the body obeys,
then the mind obeys.
If the mind obeys, then from it
the stream of jna:na flows. If it runs
unbroken, the bondage of karma loosens;
once that bondage is gone,
whatever should be seen within,
that is seen.
The very first thing taught here is
vive:ka — see that your food is good.
Even our worldly folk said the same:
"if there is food, there is muscle,
and he with muscle is the real man."
The food must be good. Whatever you
desire, that — if you want muscle,
muscle; if not,
if you want a head, a head; intellect,
intellect; something else, something else.
So the food that can give you
whatever you desire
is very important.
So this was named vive:ka.
He tried to instill this vive:ka in
the second chapter. In the third,
with the vive:ka thus gained,
the deeds you must
perform — what are they?
He named that Karma Yo:ga.
You must do tasks; the body is made
for tasks, so do them. But those
tasks — you must know how. All of them
must be done with awareness, so that
awareness He named jna:na.
Tasks refined by this jna:na
must be done — this He said in chapter
three. What kind of awareness? Again, that is
a big question. What should it be like?
It must be free of desire-driven intent.
He set a qualification for it —
in it you must have no kind of desire
whatsoever; the intention "this is
for me alone" must be shed.
Yasya sarve sama:rambha:h ka:ma-sankalpa-
varjita:h — if it is not defiled
by one's desires — then "I," "mine,"
"for me": three dangers — "I am the doer,"
"all this is mine," "it is all because
of me" — such notions form in us. So from
such things — if you can keep
the work you do in a state freed,
freed from them,
then it is like a great Agniho:tra — as
the sacred fire burns the kindling that falls in,
or the cotton, and casts it away —
so every task you then do,
sarve sama:rambha:h —
whatever the task, by the fire that is
jna:na, it becomes
well-refined karma.
If you act knowing this — letting go
of desire-driven intents — do those tasks,
do them freely. Krushna never said to
give up tasks that must be done — but behind it,
He did say to give up what must go.
What must you give up? The
attachment you have to the action —
let that go. Now do your tasks.
What happens then? Like an Agniho:tra,
they burn up all your obstacles,
cast them away, make them vanish.
Now begin doing your tasks.
These tasks He named karma. What is kept
behind — free of desire-driven intent,
that awareness which must be so —
He named jna:na.
Now there is karma, there is jna:na —
these two. Karma done; jna:na
gained within. And what is gained
must become steady. Once steady,
it must ripen into faith; that faith
must become full of love. Then do these tasks.
Then every task you do brings, to the
one on the other side who receives it,
joy. That tasks be done thus —
this He said in the third chapter.
God showed us such a one — He Himself
came that day as Krushna,
and today, for us, stands as the
archa:-mu:rthi — in the deity's form, in worship
He receives it. Thus all
the tasks you do —
how to do them, with what to do them —
this He told us.
When He said this, the Arjuna who heard
stays only within his own view; rather than
heed the words of the one speaking —
that did not much register with him.
Right then he only wants to pour out
his own fuss, his own feelings, rather than
"let me listen a little to what is said
and reflect" — that state being absent, He
seems to be saying tasks must be done.
But behind it, awareness is paramount,
He seems to say. "Awareness is paramount,
so let me fix my mind on awareness," he thinks.
"Then, work — the more you give it up,
the more you reduce it,
the more the ease," it seems to him.
"So somehow I must give this up; somehow
on jna:na I must depend." Now, "there are
two things," you say — yes. What are they? Work
is there, awareness is there;
karma is there, jna:na is there — these two.
"Now how do we manage both?"
Well, work must be done. But how
to do it? Behind it must be powerful
jna:na. "So which is paramount?" — jna:na is very
paramount, sir. "Oho — since the wealth
of jna:na is paramount, then I need not work."
He listens to His words; they seem
to make sense, but to ponder and
settle it within — lacking the capacity
for that, only halfway
does he understand. By what he understood,
he raises questions.
To somehow make it clear to him —
that is the yearning
of Sri: Krushna. The third chapter
ended thus. Jna:na
is very paramount indeed, He said;
and one wished to learn still more of it.
He explained the whole
of the fourth chapter.
He told how important jna:na is;
having said all that, at the end —
"since you have learned how great jna:na
is, get up and work," He said. "Jna:na is great,
yet You tell me to work again?
If jna:na is so great, I would gladly
give up everything, sit nicely,
and just meditate like that,
do meditation," I think — but again,
"uttishtha — uttishtha, Bha:rata!"
He said, in the fourth chapter.
"So — do you say jna:na, or karma? Of these
two, which exactly is right now —
I cannot understand, sir. Will You
make it clear?" — as he prays thus,
chapter five of the Gi:tha begins.
Let us learn the question;
let us learn the answer. Jai Sri:manna:ra:yana.