a:padam apaharta:ram da:ta:ram
sarvasampadam
lo:ka:bhi:ra:mam Shri:ra:mam bhu:yo bhu:yo
nama:myaham
Jai Shri:man Na:ra:yana!
Dear devotees of Bhagava:n,
when we start a task,
for what reason are we undertaking it,
What is its purpose?
Who all are involved in it?
What should we do?
Only after knowing these do we start the
work.
In the same way, if we want to study a
scripture,
why should we read it?
What should we know?
What is the benefit of reading it?
If we understand this and feel it is
beneficial,
then we can choose to read it or something
else.
The 'Bhagavad Gi:tha' too,
for whom is it intended?
and what is it meant to teach?
We should understand this before starting
to read the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha'.
Usually, everyone says the Bhagavad Gi:tha
is a very great scripture,
but what is its purpose?
For whom is the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha' meant?
It covers business management, personality
development, science, philosophy,
theology.
There are also many morals and other
teachings.
We often discuss the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha',
but when we actually approach that
scripture,
what should we learn from it?
What is it that we need to understand?
If we have a clear understanding,
we try to understand it from that
perspective.
If we call a Prime Minister and ask him to
clear the roads,
he can indeed clear the roads.
He might even have cleaned them himself.
But if the purpose is just to clear the
roads,
we don't actually need him for that task.
as there is someone else assigned to that
task.
there are some things that only this
person can do,
When the main benefit is to receive those
unique things from him,
then we must approach him for that
purpose.
Apart from that, when someone speaks or
acts,
whether it is good or bad,
it shows us the ignorance or incapacity we
carry.
This awareness lets us recognize
the nature of our ignorance.
Now, when we present a scripture like the
Bhagavad Gi:tha,
what is its purpose?
Is it only to teach science?
To teach science, we need scientific
books,
and we can follow those happily.
learning all those things from them.
Is it necessary to take the 'Bhagavad
Gi:tha' and learn from it?
No, we do not.
To learn morals,
we need books that teach morals,
We can go to them and learn those
principles comfortably.
Is the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha' meant to teach us
management skills?
There are many management courses,
and if we go there happily,
they will teach us all the details about
it.
we can learn from them.
Is it meant to teach us dietary rules?
There are so many doctors and physicians,
we can learn from them.
Through them we can also gain such
knowledge.
The question is not whether the Bhagavad
Gi:tha teaches this or not,
but if we understand the main goal of the
Bhagavad Gi:tha,
then wherever we go, whatever we see,
we should ask if it leads us toward that
goal or not.
Or are we able to attain that goal through
it?
It is our responsibility to know that
That is why it is our responsibility to
know it,
and understand the main purpose of the
'Bhagavad Gi:tha'.
One aspect is to make Arjuna aware of his
duty.
That was set forth as a key objective.
It was begun for that very purpose.
mainly for that reason alone.
If it were only to instruct Arjuna,
then once he was taught, the task was
done.
There would be nothing more needed.
For our times, nothing beyond that would
be required.
No, it would have remained confined to
that situation alone.
But the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha'
It is not a scripture meant only for
Arjuna,
nor solely to urge him into battle.
Then, for what purpose was it given?
It is for the human race.
When they are born on this earth,
before they die,
if they understand and do the duties they
must,
those actions become truly worthy.
This must be conveyed.
How should those duties be performed?
This guidance is essential
for all of humanity.
How should one’s dedication be?
It is crucial for a human being to
understand
that saying this
is the main purpose of Krishna's
incarnation in this world.
Arjuna,
using a certain pretext,
was part of a plan,
and through him, Krishna fulfilled it.
This is what we should understand.
There are other points as well.
yuktha:ha:ra viha:rasya,
learn how to eat properly.
yuktha svapna:vabo:dha:sya,
they say, be regulated in sleep and
wakefulness.
Such guidelines are mentioned.
There are other rules,
but to explain those rules,
what is their purpose?
What is the duty of a human being?
What should a person actually perform?
For the common man,
the Bhagavad Gi:tha came to teach this.
That is why the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha'
is divided into three parts.
The first part consists of six chapters.
The second part also consists of six
chapters,
and the third part has six chapters as
well.
Altogether, the scripture has eighteen
chapters.
The first six chapters
aim to reveal the true nature of the soul.
We don't find these teachings elsewhere,
not in management courses,
not in moral teachings,
not in scientific studies,
nor in any other places.
It is given for us to understand this
truth.
We should at least come closer to it.
To approach the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha',
you need to seek it out,
There is no need to complain that it is
not being taught.
if you don't know the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha',
there is no reason to criticize them.
We need not go searching for faults,
because the scripture itself will reach
us.
The first six chapters
are called 'A:thma Shatkam'.
They provide a detailed description of the
a:thma thatthva.
The second six chapters
are called 'Bhakti Shatkam'.
Bhakti means love,
This love must be directed towards a
certain thatthva.
It should be towards Bhagava:n, as the
Bhagavad Gi:tha teaches.
Who is this Bhagava:n in the Gi:tha?
What is his nature?
Where does he reside?
What actions does he perform?
What is your relationship with him?
What is your duty towards him?
What do you expect from him?
To what extent is that achievable?
These must be understood well,
and to explain them,
The six chapters in the middle of the
'Bhagavad Gi:tha'
are called the Bhakti Shatkam.
This is the name of the second Shatkam.
After saying this,
Arjuna had some doubts.
He thought, if I speak of these,
can I solve this?
With that courage arising,
after expressing it,
the first six chapters,
The six chapters, out of the twelve,
were arranged once again in order,
and condensed systematically.
Wherever there were gaps,
or pauses here and there,
and any points to be filled,
all of those were gathered
he combined all of them.
To present everything in full,
the last six chapters,
were given the name
Purva Sesham.
Purva se:sham,
the remainder of what was said earlier,
that is what it was named.
In this way,
it was presented
he divided it into three parts.
The scripture of eighteen chapters,
using Arjuna
as the one
for whom the reason was set,
Sri: Krushna
gave this teaching.
It is a very revered scripture,
an Adhya:thma scripture,
the Bhagavad Gi:tha.
In it,
the first four chapters
explain
the sorrow
Arjuna's heart.
That
soka
or Visha:da
is described.
His power of vive:chana was lost,
that is, the capacity to discern.
Vive:chana means
the ability to analyze.
The capacity was reduced.
What should be analyzed?
One must discern the body
the a:thma,
to see them separately,
to recognize their difference.
This discernment is crucial
to benefit from the sa:dhanas.
He spoke of seven sa:dhanas:
vimoka,
vimo:ka,
abhya:sa,
kriya,
anava:sa:da,
kalya:na, and anudharsha.
In this way,
He told us about seven sa:dhanas.
Among those seven sa:dhanas,
the very first sa:dhana
He started with is vive:kam.
Vive:kam means intelligence.
No,
vive:kam means
the ability to separate and see.
That is the meaning of
vive:chana.
What should be done in vive:chana?
That is,
the body
and the a:thma.
These two are different.
We must begin from this understanding.
How do we understand this?
how to identify the first sa:dhana?
If the food you eat is good,
everything will be good.
The food you eat should indeed be good.
If your thoughts are good,
first, you should put good food inside.
The 'indhanam' should be good.
'Indhanam' is the food we eat.
So, take in good food, dear one.
What do we mean by good food?
On what does that depend?
So we judge the quality of the food we
take.
We decide based on whether it is
sa:thvikam,
ra:jasam,
or ta:masam.
We must keep these distinctions in mind.
Whatever is not good,
we should put it aside.
Whatever is necessary,
we should accept it.
And the food we eat,
the food we eat
The influence of food,
the thoughts that arise in you,
this body,
this a:thma,
these two,
if we can analyze and see them separately,
then it is called
vivekam.
We begin with what is called aahaara
suddhi.
We start with this.
Even in our scriptures,
it is mentioned in various ways.
Aahaara Suddho, [[REVIEW: non-Gi:tha recited verse (Chandogya 7.26.2, spans cues 277-283); confirm Sanskrit transliteration + translation with a qualified Sri:vaishnava scholar]]
Sattva Suddhi,
sathva suddhau,
Dhruva Smruthi,
Smruthi Lambe,
Sarva Grandhinam,
Vipramoksha.
First, when food is pure,
then sathva, the inner quality, becomes
pure.
With sathva purified,
the mind is pure.
Sattva means mind.
When the food is good, the mind becomes
good.
And why should the mind be good?
Because, Bha:rata,
Sattva Suddho,
Dhruva Smruthi,
through a pure mind, jna:na flows to you.
For that reason,
this jna:na
must spread smoothly, without any dirt or
obstruction within it.
The dhara, the shrotas, should be clean.
Then the stream of jna:na will flow freely
like water.
If the flow of the prasadam goes on
smoothly, then it is called dhruva
smruthi.
It is the remembrance that becomes firmly
established within us.
When it proceeds in this way, doubts
inside are cleared,
all knots are untied and the true nature
is realized.
You will attain what you are meant to
attain.
As a human, you will gain what you are
born to achieve.
All the knots of karma are cut away, and
you gain true freedom.
This is what the Upanishad tells us.
Now, about the purity of food.
The first thing we take in is food,
and without food, we cannot survive.
Therefore, giving food is considered very
good.
But how do we determine if it is pure?
There are certain qualities described for
that.
One is called ja:thi dosha, a fault by the
food’s nature,
and another is a:sraya dosha,
which comes from who handles or associates
with it.
If something falls in and spoils it
temporarily, that is called nimitta.
Ja:thi, a:sraya, nimitta, adushta, annat,
ka:ya suddhi— [[REVIEW: non-Gi:tha do:sha terms run together; confirm wording + translation with a qualified scholar]]
this discernment is called vivekam.
It means we should not blame the food by
its ja:thi.
Some items naturally have certain
qualities.
Some are spicy, some are sour, and some
are sweet.
These are their characteristics.
In the same way, some are naturally
sa:thvic,
some are naturally ra:jasic,
and some are naturally tha:masic.
That is how it is.
Choose carefully what is sa:thvic by its
inherent nature.
This inherent nature is called ja:thi.
Do not allow anything of bad ja:thi to
enter you.
That is why ja:thi matters.
A:sraya.
It depends on who handles it,
and from whom it comes to you.
The influence of that person can sometimes
affect the substance,
especially if someone lacks proper
thinking,
lacks firm resolve,
and lacks the right qualification.
We must ensure that by associating with
such people, this item does not get
spoiled.
It should remain pure without being
tainted by their company.
There are faults by association,
faults by nature,
faults by association,
and faults by incidental cause.
Nimitta means something temporarily
affects it,
like something drops in for a moment.
Maybe a worm fell in,
or an ant fell in,
or a hair fell in,
These are temporary do:shas that arise
from such incidents.
which is called nimitta do:sha.
But a fault caused by nimitta is not truly
harmful.
There is the fault by ja:thi,
the fault by a:sraya,
and the fault by nimitta,
all related to food.
If you take such food as nourishment for
the body,
then the body becomes purified,
your body will obey you as you command.
When the body listens, the mind will also
listen.
When the mind listens, a stream of jna:na
will flow.
Jai Sri:manna:ra:yana! When the mind flows
steadily, the bondage of karma is
removed.
When that bondage is gone, what should be
seen within will become visible.
The very first thing mentioned here is
vivekam, discernment.
Make sure the food you eat is good and
pure.
Our elders have taught this from worldly
experience.
They said, if the food is good, the person
becomes strong and capable.
Food must be wholesome.
If you desire something, you will obtain
it.
If you wish for strength, you will get
strength.
If you wish for a head, you will get a
head.
If you wish for intelligence, you will get
intelligence.
Whatever you desire, you will receive it.
So, food is very important.
This discernment is called vive:kam.
In the 2nd chapter, he tried to bring this
vivekam to fruition.
In the 3rd chapter, he said,
he explained what actions you must do with
that vive:kam.
He called it Karma Yo:gam.
We must do work,
as the body is made to perform them.
So it naturally engages in action.
But you should know how to perform those
tasks properly.
All those actions should be done with
clarity.
Because it must be done, he called it
jna:nam.
All actions should be refined by this
He mentioned this in the 3rd chapter.
What is intelligence?
That itself is a big question, isn't it?
That intelligence must be free from desire
and resolve.
He conveyed this in the 3rd chapter.
It should have no kind of craving in it.
You must not think, 'This is only for me.'
yasya sarve: sama:rambha:ha,
ka:ma sankalpa varjitha:ha.
If we approach work without selfish
desires, three dangers arise: 'me',
'mine', and
'for me'.
One is thinking, 'I am doing it.'
Another is believing, 'All this is because
of me.'
These kinds of thoughts arise in us, don’t
they?
But if you can perform your duty free from
such notions,
that action becomes like a great
Agniho:tra,
like a sacred fire that burns up the fuel
and impurities completely.
Everything that you do is 'sarve
samarambhaha.'
Whatever task you undertake at that
point...
When done with the fire of jna:na, actions
gain noble impressions.
If you act with this understanding, they
become purifying.
So, give up attachments and do your
duties.
Krishna never said to abandon the tasks
you must do.
Krishna said this playfully — [[REVIEW: audio is "tama:sha: Krishnudu"; confirm exact sense]]
did say to let go of what must be let go.
So, what should we leave?
Let go of the deep attachment to the
action itself.
Now, perform your duties.
What happens as a result?
They burn away all obstacles like an
agni-hothram.
They remove those hindrances completely.
Now, start doing the tasks.
He named these tasks as 'karma.'
And the clear understanding free from
desire, he called 'jna:nam'.
Now there is karma and there is jna:nam.
There are two types.
Karma must be practiced outwardly,
while jna:nam is to be internalized.
What is gained should remain steady.
That steadiness should grow into firm
faith.
That faith should be rooted in love.
Then, you should carry out these tasks.
Every action done this way brings joy to
the one who receives it.
He mentioned that we should perform these
tasks in the third chapter.
Bhagava:n showed us such a person.
He gave him to us as Krishna.
Today, He stands for us as the archaa
deity,
in a form we can worship and serve.
He taught us how to perform every task and
with what attitude.
When Arjuna heard this, he felt compassion
for himself.
he remained fixed in his own viewpoint,
and did not readily accept what others
told him.
He prefers to follow his own thoughts and
feelings.
and does not even think, 'Let me listen
and reflect on what is said.'
So he says we should do the work,
but he emphasizes that intelligence is
crucial.
If intelligence is primary, let us focus
on that.
He feels content if we cease doing the
work.
We should cease doing the work,
and focus on knowledge.
Now, there are two aspects, as we say,
there is work and there is intelligence.
There is karma and there is knowledge.
Both action and jna:na are there, these
two exist.
Now, how do we handle both of them?
We must engage in action.
Then, how should we do it?
There must be strength from jna:na behind
it.
What is important?
Knowledge is very important.
Oh, since jna:na is important, should we
stop acting?
He is listening to the words,
and he seems to understand them,
but he does not have the chance to reflect
deeply
and firmly establish them within himself.
He's only partially understanding it.
He is questioning himself if he has truly
understood it.
Sri: Krishna is eager to make him
understand fully.
That is how the third chapter concludes.
He said, 'Jna:na is very important, dear
one.'
He wanted to learn more about it.
He explained the fourth chapter as well,
He spoke about how crucial jna:na is.
After all that, he said, 'Now that you
know its greatness...'
'...stand up and do your duty.'
Arjuna wonders, 'If jna:na is supreme, why
tell me to work again?'
He repeats, 'Jna:na is great, yet you must
act.'
If we think, ‘Since jna:na is supreme, let
us give up everything and sit in
meditation’,
then in the fourth chapter Bhagava:n says,
‘A:thishtta, yogam a:thishtta, utthishtta
Bha:rata!’
Now, is that jna:na or is it karma? Which
is it?
I am unable to grasp which of the two is
truly right.
Please clarify this for me.
While we pray in this way,
If we pray like this, the fifth chapter of
the Bhagavad Gi:tha begins.
Let us understand the question,
and let us know the answer.
Jai Shri:man Na:ra:yana!