a:padam apaharta:ram da:ta:ram
sarvasampadam
lo:ka:bhi:ra:mam Shri:ra:mam bhu:yo bhu:yo
nama:myaham
Jai Shri:man Na:ra:yana!
Dear devotees of Bhagava:n,
when we start a task,
why are we doing that work?
What is its purpose?
Who all are involved in it?
What should we do?
We begin that task after understanding all
these aspects.
Similarly, if we want to read a book,
why should we read it?
What should we know?
What is the benefit of reading it?
If we understand this and feel it is
beneficial,
then we can decide to read another book.
The 'Bhagavad Gi:tha' too,
for whom is it intended?
What should we know?
We should understand this before starting
to read the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha'.
Generally, everyone says that the
'Bhagavad Gi:tha' is a great book,
but what is its purpose?
For whom is the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha' meant?
It covers business management, personality
development, science, philosophy,
theology.
It contains many morals.
We often discuss the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha',
but when we open that book,
what should we learn from it?
What should we understand from it?
If we have a clear understanding,
we try to understand it from that
perspective.
If we call a Prime Minister and ask him to
clear the roads,
he can indeed clear the roads.
He has already arranged for the roads to
be cleaned.
But if the purpose is just to clear the
roads,
he does not need to do it himself,
as there is someone else assigned to that
task.
there are some things that only this
person can do,
so when it is important for us to learn
from him,
we should approach him.
Other than that, when a person says
something,
whether it is good or bad,
it reveals what kind of ignorance we have.
This understanding helps us see
the nature of our ignorance.
When we present a book like the 'Bhagavad
Gi:tha',
what is its purpose?
Is it only to teach science?
To teach science, we need scientific
books,
and we can follow those happily.
We can learn from them.
Is it necessary to take the 'Bhagavad
Gi:tha' and learn from it?
It is not necessary.
To learn morals,
we need books that teach morals,
and we can learn from those happily.
Is the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha' meant to teach us
management skills?
There are many management courses,
and if we go there happily,
they will teach us all the details about
it.
we can learn from them.
Is it meant to teach us dietary rules?
There are so many doctors and physicians,
we can learn from them.
But is the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha' meant to
teach or not?
If we know the purpose of the 'Bhagavad
Gi:tha',
then wherever we go, whatever we see,
we should ask, will it take us to that
goal?
Or are we able to reach that goal through
it?
Is it meant to teach or not?
It is our responsibility to know that
That is why it is our responsibility to
know it,
and understand the main purpose of the
'Bhagavad Gi:tha'.
In this context,
it was to teach Arjuna his duty.
He started for that purpose,
mainly for that reason alone.
After teaching Arjuna,
his work was complete.
There was no need for anything else.
We don't need anything more in this era.
No, it was left solely for that purpose.
But the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha'
is not a book only for Arjuna
or just for the war.
Then, what is it for?
It is for the human race.
When they are born on this earth,
before they die,
if they do the work they are supposed to
do,
they will be able to achieve it.
This must be conveyed.
How should they perform the work they are
meant to do?
For the human race,
this is important.
How should they fulfill their duty?
It is crucial for a human being to
understand
that saying this
is the main purpose of Krishna's
incarnation in this world.
Arjuna,
with a specific purpose,
was part of a plan,
and through him, Krishna fulfilled it.
This is what we should understand.
There are additional aspects to this.
yuktha:ha:ra viha:rasya,
learn how to eat properly.
yuktha svapna:vabo:dha:sya,
early to bed, early to rise.
There are guidelines like these.
There are other rules,
but to explain those rules,
what is their purpose?
What is the duty of a human being?
What should he do?
For the common man,
this is the purpose of the 'Bhagavad
Gi:tha'.
That is why the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha'
is divided into three parts.
The first part consists of six chapters.
The second part also consists of six
chapters,
and the third part has six chapters as
well.
Altogether, there are eighteen chapters.
The first six chapters
aim to reveal the true nature of the soul.
We don't find these teachings elsewhere,
not in management courses,
not in moral teachings,
not in scientific studies,
nor in any other places.
To understand these concepts,
you must turn to the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha'.
To approach the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha',
you need to seek it out,
and you have to understand it.
if you don't know the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha',
there's no need to worry.
You don't have to search for it,
because it will come to you.
The first six chapters
are called 'A:thma Shatkam'.
They provide a detailed description of the
a:thma thatthva.
The second six chapters
are called 'Bhakti Shatkam'.
Bhakti means love,
and you must have this love in any
thatthva.
This love is emphasized in the 'Bhagavad
Gi:tha'.
Who is the one in the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha'?
What is his nature?
Where does he reside?
What will he do?
What is your relationship with him?
What do you have to do with him?
What do you expect from him?
How far is that possible?
You have to know all these,
to understand the essence of the 'Bhagavad
Gi:tha'.
The six chapters in the middle of the
'Bhagavad Gi:tha'
are called the Bhakti Shatkam.
This is the name of the second Shatkam.
After saying this,
Arjuna had some doubts.
If I say this,
can I solve this?
He had the courage,
and after saying this,
the first six chapters,
the second six chapters,
out of the twelve chapters,
he followed a systematic order.
He did a thorough analysis.
There are some pauses,
some connecting points,
and if there are any,
he combined all of them.
To convey all of them,
the last six chapters,
he called it
Purva Sesham.
Migulu.
He called it
In this way,
he divided it into three parts.
Chapter 18
is the Grantham.
Arjuna,
as a reason,
Sri: Krushna
considered it an important
Grantham,
Adhya:thma Grantham,
the 'Bhagavad Gi:tha'.
In this,
the first four chapters
address
Arjuna's heart.
A
soka
or Visha:da
needed to be opened.
He needed
vive:chana.
Vive:chana means
the ability to analyze.
The capacity was reduced.
What should be analyzed?
The body.
the a:thma,
to be able to analyze,
to be able to discern,
is very important
to benefit from the sa:dhanas.
God said,
vimoka,
abhya:sa,
kriya,
anava:sa:da,
kalya:na,
anudharsha.
In this way,
He told us about seven sa:dhanas.
Among those seven sa:dhanas,
the very first sa:dhana
He started with is vive:kam.
Vive:kam means intelligence.
No,
vive:kam means
the ability to separate and see.
That is the meaning of
vive:chana.
What should be done in vive:chana?
That is,
the body
and the a:thma.
These two are different.
We should start from here.
How do we know
how to identify the first sa:dhana?
If the food you eat is good,
everything will be good.
The food you eat should indeed be good.
If your thoughts are good,
first, you should put good food inside.
The 'indhanam' should be good.
'Indhanam' is the food we eat.
So, should we put good food inside?
So, what is considered good food?
Depending on what,
we determine the goodness of the food.
We decide based on whether it is
sa:thvikam,
ra:jasam,
or ta:masam.
We should remember these categories.
Whatever is not good,
we should put it aside.
Whatever is necessary,
we should accept it.
And the food we eat,
the food we eat
affects us.
Whatever thoughts you have,
this body,
this a:thma,
these two,
if we are able to separate and see,
then it is called
vivekam.
Aahaara Suddhi.
We start with this.
Even in our scriptures,
this is said:
Aahaara Suddho,
Sattva Suddhi,
Sattva Suddho,
Dhruva Smruthi,
Smruthi Lambe,
Sarva Grandhinam,
Vipramoksha.
First, Aahaara Suddho.
If the food is pure,
Sattva Suddhi,
the mind is pure.
Sattva means mind.
If the food is pure,
the mind is pure.
Why should the mind be pure?
Sattva Suddho,
Dhruva Smruthi,
the mind gives you knowledge.
That's why
this knowledge
if the prasadam should flow smoothly, then
there should not be any kind of dirt or
impurities in it.
The dhara, the shrotas, should be clean.
If there is any kind of jna:na in the
prasadam, then it should flow smoothly.
If the flow of the prasadam goes on
smoothly, then it is called dhruva
smruthi.
If there is any kind of dirt or impurities
in the prasadam, then it is called
smaranam.
If the flow of the prasadam continues
smoothly, then all the impurities will be
removed.
As a result, all impurities in the
prasadam will vanish.
You will receive everything you need.
You will obtain everything a human being
requires.
Thus, all impurities in the prasadam will
be eliminated.
Consequently, you will receive everything
necessary.
This is what the Upanishad teaches.
The food should be clean,
and the first thing we consume is food.
Without it, we cannot live.
That is why it is good to give food.
But how do we make it clean?
There are certain characteristics to
consider.
Among them, one is called jati tahakani,
and another is called asriya dosha.
It is called nimitta.
Jati, asriya, nimitta, adushta, annat,
kayasuddhihi.
This is known as vivekam.
It should not be referred to as jati
dosha.
Some things have specific characteristics.
Some are spicy, some are sour, and some
are sweet.
These are their characteristics.
Similarly, certain things possess specific
traits.
Some things have particular
characteristics,
and some things have distinct features.
Certain things have unique attributes.
You should select and choose things based
on these characteristics.
This is jati.
Don't let negative influences affect you.
That is why jati is important.
Asriya.
Some people end up on the wrong path,
and others follow them.
Sometimes, the bad influence affects the
person who is not thinking properly,
who is not content,
and who has no appropriate or deserved
path.
Such a person is easily led astray.
Justice should be given as per the example
of Sri: Yudhishthira.
The association is not corrupted.
The caste is not corrupted.
The cause is not corrupted.
Nimitta means something temporarily
affects it,
something falls temporarily.
Something fell.
There are some do:shas that fall
temporarily,
which is called nimitta do:sha.
Nimitta do:sha is not bad.
Ja:thi adushtathu,
a:sraya adushtathu,
nimitta adushtathu,
annama:thu.
If you take such food as nourishment for
the body,
ka:ya suddhihi,
your body will obey you as you command.
If your body obeys you, then your mind
will follow.
And if your mind follows, you will gain
knowledge from it.
If your mind listens to you, you will gain
karma.
When your mind listens to you, you will
gain karma.
The first word in this context is vivekam.
Ensure that your food is wholesome.
Our ancestors have emphasized this since
ancient times.
By eating good food, you will become a
virtuous person.
By consuming good food, you will become a
If you desire something, you will obtain
it.
If you desire a head, you will receive a
head.
If you desire intelligence, you will gain
intelligence.
If you desire something else, you will
acquire that too.
Whatever you desire, you will receive it.
So, food is very important.
This is called vivekam (discrimination).
In the 2nd chapter, he tried to bring this
vivekam to fruition.
In the 3rd chapter, he said,
what are the activities you should perform
with this vivekam?
He called it Karma Yo:gam.
You should engage in tasks,
as the body is made to perform them.
That is why it naturally does tasks.
But you should know how to perform those
tasks properly.
You should understand the right way to
execute them.
That is why he referred to it as Jna:nam.
You should undertake tasks that are
aligned with Jna:nam.
He mentioned this in the 3rd chapter.
What is intelligence?
That is a significant question.
To possess intelligence, you should have a
strong desire for it.
He conveyed this in the 3rd chapter.
You should not have any desire.
But you should have a strong desire.
yasya sarve: sama:rambha:ha,
ka:ma sankalpa varjitha:ha.
If you do not have a strong desire, then
there are three dangers.
One is thinking, 'I am doing it.'
Another is believing, 'All this is because
of me.'
These things happen to us, right?
If you are able to do the task that you
are supposed to do,
it is like a big fire,
a big fire that burns everything.
Everything that you do is 'sarve
samarambhaha.'
No matter what task you do,
it is like a big fire that burns
everything.
Yes, it is like a big fire that burns
If you know this, you can do it.
But you should not do the tasks that you
are supposed to avoid.
Ta:mar Shah Krishna,
he asked us to leave what we should leave.
So, what should we leave?
If you have a strong desire, leave the
task that you are supposed to leave.
Now, do the tasks you are meant to do.
What will happen because of that?
It is like a big fire that burns
everything.
It will make you lose everything.
Now, start doing the tasks.
He named these tasks as 'karma.'
He named these tasks as 'jna:nam.'
Now there is karma and there is jna:nam.
There are two types.
Karma is to be performed,
while jna:nam is to be internalized.
Jna:nam should be firm,
and jna:nam should be practiced with
faith.
That faith should be rooted in love.
Then, you should carry out these tasks.
Whoever performs these tasks will find
happiness.
He mentioned that we should perform these
tasks in the third chapter.
God presented us with such a person.
He gave him to us as Krishna.
Now, he stands as an idol for us,
an idol who delights in our worship.
He instructed us on how to perform all the
tasks we are meant to do.
When Arjuna heard this, he felt compassion
for himself.
He is always guided by his own vision.
He doesn't want to heed what others say.
He prefers to follow his own thoughts and
feelings.
He wants to engage in the work,
but he emphasizes that intelligence is
crucial.
He wants to concentrate on intelligence.
He feels content if we cease doing the
work.
We should cease doing the work,
and focus on knowledge.
There are two types of knowledge:
there is work and there is intelligence.
There is karma and there is knowledge.
There are two types of knowledge.
How do we approach these two types of
knowledge?
We should perform the work.
Then, how should we do it?
We should have knowledge supporting us.
What is important?
Knowledge is very important.
Indeed, knowledge is crucial.
We should perform the work.
He is listening to what is being said,
and he is understanding it.
But he doesn't have the opportunity to
reflect on it.
He is not able to fully grasp it.
He is questioning himself if he has truly
understood it.
Sri: Krishna wants to ensure that he has
comprehended it.
That is how the third chapter concludes.
He emphasized that knowledge is very
important.
He wanted to learn more about it.
He explained the fourth chapter as well,
highlighting the importance of knowledge.
In the end, he acknowledged the
significance of knowledge.
He urged him to rise and perform the work.
He reiterated that knowledge is very
important.
He encouraged him to do the work once
more.
He said that if knowledge is very
important,
then he might abandon everything and sit
down to meditate.
He stated that yoga is the ultimate, and
the ultimate is Bharata.
Do you consider this as knowledge or
karma?
I don't understand which of the two is
correct.
Please explain it to me.
If we pray like this, the fifth chapter of
the Bhagavad Gi:tha begins.
Let us understand the question,
and let us know the answer.
Jai Shri:man Na:ra:yana!